[music]
[Ben] This is the Tennessee home
for the incurables.
I think it opened in like 1906.
And it was a place for people with terminal
illnesses like tuberculosis, quadriplegics,
yellow fever, stuff that used to
kill everybody, they would end up here.
This building is almost like
a metaphor for Memphis.
You got something here,
the bones are great.
You can see this place
has a ton of potential.
It's just been neglected
and fallen into disrepair for 25 years now.
[Peter] So we're gonna get into it today,
your guys' stories.
You were on the streets, deep into drugs.
Came out and now are getting people
off the streets who are into drugs.
-Bingo, and our story started
right around here
Your in the epicenter of
where all our madness took place.
In fact we probably both
shoulda died on the street right next door.
But Jess and I,
the whole time we were out here
we had this fox hole prayer
that if God would get us out of
hell together we'd come back for everybody
and so when we came back to Memphis
we came right back here
and this is where it all started.
It's taken over by squatters
and the criminal element.
Lost people.
You don't just get addicted to the dope.
You get addicted to the chaos.
You get addicted to the insanity,
the excitement.
And so what I see end up happening a lot
is people get clean.
They'll go get a job,
get back in their kids' lives.
They're rebuilding,
and there's no excitement.
-Right.
We've baked chaos into what we do.
That's why we're out here, it's not just
because this is where the addicts are.
This is where I love to be.
And I think for most addicts,
we miss the unpredictability,
the uncertainty that happens out here,
but we still want to stay clean.
So if you can find a way
to bring people out of addiction,
get them into recovery,
and right back in the damn hood,
you check that chaos box.
-Totally makes sense.
You know, on Skid Row,
a lot of those guys
can get the housing if they want to.
-But you've got to play by the rules.
-Yeah.
And a guy told me
I love the adventure of it.
-Yeah, 100%. Absolutely.
-The adrenaline of it.
And if you're going into normie society,
like living in the burbs 9:00 to 5:00.
-Driving a commute every day.
-That sucks.
-From the adventure.
-Yeah.
-I get the adventure out of making videos.
-Right.
We still get to be in the thick of it.
We had a couple of Green Berets from
Fort Campbell over here
three four weeks ago,
and we had a random gunshot
on one of our blocks.
This combat medic Green Beret dude
ends up getting to treat a gunshot wound
right here in his backyard.
And stuff like that happens
all the time.
I don't want to make it sound like
we enjoy it when that happens,
but that's part of the insanity
that keeps us
on the right path, I guess.
Gotcha.
-How long you guys been clean?
-Seven years.
We left the streets
almost seven years ago exactly.
In fact, I'm gonna take you over there.
My rock bottom happened in two places,
and one of them was right there.
Today, we own that house.
We own the house next door to it.
We've got women and kids housed here,
but that used to be the trap house.
In fact, every bit of violence that
happened, I would say within a mile radius,
maybe more of that house
was fueled by that house.
This street right here,
which looks like a little
quiet hood suburban street,
used to be the most violent street
in South Memphis.
And today, I don't even know the last time
that a violent crime happened there.
Pretty much the day we took control
of that trap house, the street got calm.
Kids are coming outside again.
-Okay, explain a trap house.
Okay, so a trap house where
narcotics and women are bought and sold.
They are the single source of suffering
for any neighborhood in which they exist.
Every bit of chaos
emanates from the trap.
All the criminal activity
goes back to the trap.
It's basically where
the criminal element sets up shop.
-Many trap houses still in Memphis?
Oh, tons, yeah.
It's gotten a lot better since
Memphis State Task Force came here.
They've hit a lot of
the more known traps.
But the biggest problem you run into
out here is lack of economic opportunity.
So if I go shut down a trap house,
that economic opportunity still exists.
It's gonna pop right back up
in a different house.
-And they're probably just gonna get more
secretive and better with it, right?
-You would think.
-No?
Maybe in a different city,
but here in Memphis, not so much, man.
-Okay.
-They don't change sh*t.
The names and the addresses change,
but the methods, it all stays the same.
-Can we get out there?
-Oh, absolutely.
Back when the street was being run
as a dope track, this was the trap house.
This is the one
I was just telling you about.
That was a rooming house.
I used to squat in that one.
We've since torn the house down.
We just rebuilt that.
-Oh, nice. Looks good.
Both of these are ours.
Hey! How you doing?
-[woman] My hands are dirty.
-Why?
-Gardening.
-This is Cheyenne.
I'm doing strawberries,
peas, and potatoes.
Who all is home?
Pretty sure Mama and Rekia.
Oh, hell yeah.
This was the trap house.
Me and Jess have smoked
copious amounts of dope in here.
I've seen people die in this house.
I had a dude put a pistol to my head
and pull the trigger.
I don't know why it didn't go off.
I had a dude try to shoot me
behind this house.
-When you say dope, was it fentanyl? Meth?
No, crack and heroin.
So this train track right here,
there's this one
and another one right up there.
And what used to happen,
you see one stopped?
The one that hits Southern stops, too.
You'll get boxed in between these two.
And back in the day
when that would happen,
that's when things would get
real violent out here real quick.
-Real quick.
-No way!
Because the cops couldn't, there's nobody,
no EMS can't get in.
So any beef that needed to get squashed
would usually get squashed
when these trains are both stopped.
This was a scary place to be.
It's obviously very different today.
This and Woodward were
the two worst streets in South Memphis.
You're in the 38106 zip code,
which historically is one of the most
impoverished zip codes in America.
Violent crime rate here
is through the roof.
If you're a young Black male living here
2020 to 2023,
you're five times more likely
to die a violent death than a soldier
serving in the Global War on Terror
the same year.
Or actually any year.
Your risk of death if you're fighting
in combat in Iraq or Afghanistan
was about 25 in 100,000.
Young Black males in this zip code,
your risk of death is 130 in 100,000.
Five times more likely to die
as a civilian in South Memphis
than you are fighting
the Global War on Terror.
-That's insane.
-Yeah.
It's actually, let's remove that from
the equation and just say civilian period.
Your risk of death in Memphis
to being murdered is about 55 in 100,000.
Just being a civilian in Memphis
is twice as deadly as fighting in combat.
-Try to wrap your mind around that one.
-Yeah.
So the only way is to get out,
is that the story for these kids?
So, you know, you got kids
that are growing up on these streets.
A lot of them get put in
the game, they call it.
Yep.
Selling dope a lot of times
to help mama put food on the table.
They get incarcerated for the first time,
usually between ages 12 and 15.
And every one of them
down to a man will tell you
that's what taught them
to become a better criminal.
What's up, bro?
How you doing, man?
-What's up, man?
-What's up, buddy?
[Peter] How you doing?
-You good today, man?
-Good to see you, bro.
Good to see you, man.
-It's been a minute.
-Peter, nice to meet you.
-It's good to see you, dude.
-We're making a video, guys.
You've been here, what, 15 years?
I've been here over 30.
Oh, no sh*t.
-You've seen a lot here?
-Yeah.
-Oh, God.
-A whole lot.
40 years of this street.
You've seen murders, what?
Yeah. There was one guy.
He had just came from the Army.
Got pissed off at us out here.
Just came out here and just got to
shooting at us and everything, man.
He was an old guy, though.
He was in a wheelchair.
He had one of his legs cut off
or something.
-He was in a wheelchair with a gun?
-Yeah.
He used to wheel hisself,
you know, he used to mess with them.
He used to mess with
the whores that come over.
Callgirls, they used to come over.
-So that house I showed you
used to be a brothel.
-Yeah.
-No way.
Yeah, that used to be a whorehouse.
So did law enforcement just avoid this zone
back in the day or were they here?
-MPD wouldn't come.
Yeah. They never come.
They'll come,
but they couldn't find nothing.
They'll come
but they just wouldn’t hit the brakes.
And it's a dead end
so they didn't want to come on the street.
They wouldn't even come down here.
They said, "God damn it,
they ain't want a better… and all that.
They ain't want to stop and get…
They couldn't get nothing.
They couldn't find any drugs.
So they just started taking his equipment.
-How long you been sober, man?
-Seven years.
-Seven years, man.
-Congratulations, brother.
Appreciate that. It means a lot.
Congratulations for real.
And then there's a lot of them
can't get themselves up.
-Nah.
-For real.
They need a lot of help.
[Peter] What's the drug situation
right now? Getting worse? Better?
-Worse.
-It's worse.
You got little kids,
13, 14, 15-year-old kids on it.
Every neighborhood
in this surrounding area, man.
-Drugs.
-He's been here for a while.
-Fentanyl's the main thing, or what?
-Yeah.
Fentanyl, crack, and heroin.
They can't afford it.
So they just… Yeah.
I don't even remember
the last time I saw heroin.
50 cent to a dollar.
So at least 50 at a time.
-You buying in bulk.
-You buy in bulk, okay.
Yeah, 50 cent to a dollar.
-So that 50 cent a pill,
how much does that sell for on the street?
You can get it for five or ten bucks.
-Yeah, but…
-Just like they sell…
It's like $2.00, $3.00 a piece, man.
When fent first started coming out here
and they're doing the press 30s,
our dumb ass were still paying
30 bucks a pill.
Cause they used to go for
a dollar a milligram.
Once Fent got out here, it changed
the economics significantly.
You're not having to deal with
diversion from pharmacies.
It's being pressed at industrial scale
in labs in Mexico now.
-It's in everything now.
-Yeah, it's in all of it.
It's in everything.
-Okay, what's the point of that?
From a dealer's standpoint?
Why would you do that?
If they can make it more addictive,
they're gonna sell more of it.
And then there's a lot of what happens is
it's accidentally getting mixed.
If you've ever been in a trap house
where they're serving dope.
You got White powder in two places,
coke here, fent here.
It ends up getting accidentally mixed.
-It's not like Swiss pharmacy standards.
-No, exactly.
Then they're taking the card
and they scraping it on the same scale.
And it's so potent.
It only takes a couple of grains of fent
getting mixed in with your coke
for you to cook up some crack and hit it.
And you're done. It's over with.
So what was the catalyst
for getting into the drugs?
Did you grow up
like in a super bad family?
-No.
-You got ostracized?
My parents are still married.
They live 10 minutes
up the street in Georgia.
I had a perfect childhood. My dad was
an Army Ranger. My mom was an engineer.
She helped build
the Columbia Space Shuttle.
-No way!
-I was gifted.
No way.
We moved to California when I was 13
and I started struggling with anxiety
really, really bad
and ADHD.
Docs put me on Ritalin and that's
really where my addiction started.
-It was Ritalin, Adderall.
-Interesting.
That fueled the anxiety.
-And I discovered alcohol at 13 too.
-Okay.
Alcohol was always my biggest problem.
I dabbled in drugs, you know,
all of them when I was 14, 15.
Ended up in residential treatment.
Got it together.
Went back, finished college,
started a family, did all that.
And then I got in
a really bad car wreck in 2007
and started dealing with
recurrent staph infections from it.
And so I ended up on pain meds.
And ended up addicted
to the pain meds in 2011, I think.
-Okay.
Well, that progressed and you heard
the conversation we just had.
You know, a dollar a milligram
for pain pills is pretty d*mned expensive.
And when you have a tolerance
that adds up quick.
I ended up with a $600 a day
pain pill habit.
-Were you on Oxy or what?
-Yeah, yeah. I was on Oxys.
I ended up hiring a guy
who had a heroin habit.
And he introduced me to heroin.
And it was, in the beginning,
exponentially cheaper than pain meds.
And I was like, this is great.
And it feels better.
But that didn't last long.
within a matter of days
from the first time I shot up,
what had been a
$300 to $600 a day pain pill habit
ended up becoming
an $800 a day heroin habit.
How'd you afford that?
Well, I owned a business.
And I was doing pretty good.
-What kind of business?
-It was electronics recycling.
So we were buying truckloads
of freight-damaged flat-screen TVs.
Okay.
We would test and sell
the parts to the industry.
There were very few of us in the world.
And you could operate on that level
of intoxication or drug usage?
-Not really.
-Okay.
-So that's why I ended up going downhill.
I think it was 10 months on heroin
that first go around
before I got arrested for the first time.
I had two businesses,
the electronics distributorship,
and then we also had a tactical brand.
And so I got pulled over
with a bunch of guns.
And what at the time
I thought was a ton of dope,
I had like six grams of dope on me.
And that's next to nothing now
with the work we do today.
But they charged me
like I was Pablo Escobar.
So I went from no criminal record,
Cub Scout master, you know,
T-ball coach, business owner, employer,
to being charged
with 14 felonies overnight.
Okay. So that must have been brutal because
the community, all the people you knew,
probably were like, what happened to Ben?
Exactly. We lived out in Lakeland,
which is a suburb.
We were on a golf course.
And I was instantly a pariah.
You know, the news went out there.
I was PNG'd from everywhere.
But these guys out here
welcomed me back with open arms.
Of course they did. I had money.
I ended up basically
moving into this house.
This was back in 2014.
The house didn't look
anything like this back then.
-It looked like maybe that over there?
-Exactly like that.
-Worse than that actually.
-Like that?
Like this, yeah.
So I moved into this house and ended up
living over there with prostitutes.
-Like how did you end up here?
The drugs brought you?
Drugs brought me. Yeah.
So it's just like word on the street
where to go?
Yeah. Well, it was… [sighs]
Obviously, I was the only White guy
out here, you know?
And so it was a process of earning trust.
Lucretia, what's up, girl?
-Okay, yeah. What was that like?
Hey, 'Cretia. She can talk about this.
Lucretia, she's a few years
out of the game herself now.
She's clean. She lives with her wife,
couple of her grandkids.
Hey, Peter. Nice to meet you.
Where we meet, 'Cretia?
On ward.
Your hand coming through the window.
Snatched some dope off the table.
-Wait, wait. What was that?
-He snatched dope off the table.
'Cretia used to sell dope and women.
You have men coming over wanting
to get high, find a woman.
They'll pay me, I'm going' out there
and find 'em, bring ' back.
-Okay, you were the middle man.
-Middle man for they money.
-Long as I get mine.
-It'll blow your mind.
-20 bucks out here, dude.
-20 bucks!?
I've seen women turn tricks
for half a pack of Newports.
-Or a nickel rock.
-Or a $5 rock of crack.
It's sad. I mean, it is bad.
Rikaya! Hey, baby!
We actually fostered her,
well, my business partner did,
while her mom was getting help.
Her mom's doing great now.
-Okay, so Ben, just to wrap up on,
you came into this house.
How was it letting
the White guy into town?
-Suspect.
-Suspect?
We didn't have White people
just come to the windows or doors.
We were like, you the po-po.
You thought he was po-po.
He looks like po-po.
-I look like po-po.
-Yeah, he came one day bloody.
-Knocked him out.
-Yeah.
-Who knocked him out?
-Jess.
Used to beat the hell out of me.
Okay, and so you guys.
And then he hid his door in the car.
That's how far down we fell, man.
We lived in a f*cking car.
I had a lot of up and down, man.
We met after I got arrested
that first time.
I was court ordered
into Narcotics Anonymous.
That's where we met.
We ended up relapsing together
and lost the house that I had
out on the golf course.
Got a bigger house.
Got the businesses back off the ground.
Got a way bigger house and then decided
to start getting high again.
And that's when
I brought Jess out to South Memphis.
And so Jess got introduced to this house,
to 'Crecia and her house.
-How long have you been clean?
Going on three.
-Three years?
-Yeah.
What do you do to fill the void?
Taking care of baby and working every day
and taking care of the house.
Looks good.
She's under selling it. She's brought
a dozen kids through this house.
They'll foster.
They've fostered an entire family
the school year before last.
Mom, dad, three kids.
We didn't tell them to.
They rent this house.
They can do whatever they want.
But they're paying it forward.
Staying in the middle of all the chaos,
like we were talking about.
The lady down there run down here
when her little boyfriend beat up.
-Yep.
-We had her.
Yeah. This is like, this is a safe house.
And the one next door is too.
[man] Yes. My lovely girl.
So this is the first house
Chris renovated.
We spent $300,000
fixing this house property.
-No way.
-Yeah.
I had no idea what I was doing.
He had just come to us
straight out of custody.
He's done over half his life incarcerated.
He had no teeth and one eye
when he came to us.
And this is like my closure house.
I should have died in here.
My blood was still on the floor
when we came in here the first time.
My friend's blood was still on the floor
back there, you know.
And Chris was like,
man, I know how to renovate houses.
And I was like,
well, let's go figure it out.
Let's get to work
and see what we get done.
And here we are, you know.
[Peter] Okay. So back here
is where you almost got executed?
-Yeah.
And so many people died out here, man.
This was hell for a long time.
The street, we called the street hell.
That was the door to hell.
The front was barricaded.
The back door is where we had to go in.
-So are there still parts of Memphis
that were like what this was before?
100% man. Yeah.
-We can cruise by some of these today?
Yeah, we'll go. I'm not gonna take you in.
-Sure, of course.
-'Cause you have a camera.
They won't like that,
but I'll take you by some traps.
Some of them are being run by dudes
whose other traps we already shut down.
Like they helped us shut them down,
but they still got to go make a living.
-So you're not well liked?
-I'm very well liked by them.
-The guys that you're shutting down.
-Yeah, they still like us.
Why?
Because I've gotten their
baby mama's help, their mom off of dope.
I've gotten their sister
to stop selling her body.
They love what we do.
I'm not trying
to send the dope boys to jail ever.
In fact, when they get rolled up,
we're working with the district attorney,
whoever we can
to get them on a better path.
Because I want to see…
We're not gonna fix the problem out here
without the dope boys leading the charge.
I'm, you know, a bald White dude
covered in tattoos.
The younger generation of Memphis
is not gonna listen to me.
I need those OGs. I need the dope boys.
I need them to come back out here
and carry a message of hope
saying you ain't gotta live this way.
You don't have to go to prison.
This life doesn't have anything for you.
Let's do this, this, and this instead.
So we're trying, like…
The dope boys do love what we do.
-This is one of
the new houses you've done.
We call this Sparrow 2.
These are the houses for women and kids
coming out of human trafficking.
Chris helped build this one?
-Chris designed this from the ground up.
-Nice, Chris.
-And built it.
-That's cool, man. You got skills.
God is good, bro.
This is a much nicer one.
You know, lots of people, when they're
doing a house for people out of addiction
and, you know,
trafficking women or something,
they're just kind of trying to
throw something together.
I didn't want it thrown together.
I wanted something very nice.
-Yep.
-I wanted clean, nice.
Something that they could be proud of,
Something that they could
feel worthy of living in it.
Because that's important
and a lot of them had a rough childhood.
I had a rough childhood where I had
cabinets and the doors were hanging off,
and the counters were peeling.
And a lot of them
come from houses like that.
So I thought it was very important
for them to be able to come to a place
where they could feel good.
-That's huge, right? Psychologically?
-Yes.
Having a nice space like this.
And then, Chris, that's gotta feel good.
Like, you got to get purpose
in building these things.
I'll be honest with you, man.
I was strung out all my life.
And then I said a prayer to God
asking Him for help.
And that's when He put
Ben and Jess in my life.
And they never looked at my past, man.
They just gave me a chance.
I get purpose out of it.
Now I strive to help others
as well as myself.
So I do a lot of the work myself
because it saves money.
'Cause when you have subcontractors,
they want top dollar.
Okay, so the first one was $300,000.
How much was this one?
What can you get?
This house here is like $130,000, $140,000.
But the difference is
he was trying to help
everybody in the halfway house have a job.
Tying to teach them trades
and careers in doing this house.
And they didn't know anything
about construction.
So he was out of a bunch of money
from pocket because of that.
-The way I have to look at this is,
like, my product is not housing.
My product is human lives. You know?
And you look at
these two dudes right here.
Worth every penny of $300,000.
And they're not the only two
that benefited from it.
That changed Chris's life.
It changed Tammy's life.
It gave Rekia a place to live.
You know, you can't put dollars on that.
None of this new construction is happening.
And it just goes to show, man,
all it takes to change
the dynamic on one street
is one person giving a f*ck. That's it.
Oh, Lord!
-That's what you're talking about.
Yeah.
And there's another train track behind us.
Okay.
So back in the day, does it still happen?
-This dynamic of the trains?
-No. They will still knock cars off.
So I used to live in this house,
1420 East McLemore.
That garage behind it,
They'll knock off train cars
and go hide merchandise in that garage.
-Seriously?
-Yeah.
I haven't seen it happen in about a year.
-[Jess] Yeah.
-But they used to.
This is Shady Lane that were on now
and everything about this street is shady.
-Used to be shady.
-It looks pretty good.
-These are cool homes actually.
-There's a really cool one here.
I want this one actually… bad.
-Right, nice old brick homes,
steep roofs.
That one's new or redone.
For deep hood, this actually
looks pretty good, I gotta say.
Right. So you're in one of
the more historic areas right now.
-Okay.
One statistic I meant to give you,
this is very important.
Young men out here
are more likely to be dead or incarcerated
than to have a job or be in school.
-That single data point right there is…
-Tells you everything.
Yeah, exactly.
If we could change that you could change
the whole dynamic out here.
Oh, my God. These trains are killing me.
-That's a cool train though.
-Oh, my God. Bro, it's tanks!
[Ben] What in the hell?
When you're on the ground talking
to everyday people behind the headlines,
you realize how different reality can be
from what the media delivers us.
The same story can be spun
in completely different ways.
That's why I use Ground News.
You pull in thousands of articles
from around the world
and organize them by story
so you can see how the left, center,
and right are covering the same event.
Their color-coded layout shows
each outlet's political bias.
Take this same story about
the Memphis Safe Task Force.
A right-leaning outlet
leads with the headline,
Lawsuit hits Trump's Memphis Task Force
as marshals reveal 9,000 arrests
and 1,500 guns seized.
While a left-leaning journal
frames the story,
Memphis residents
claim harassment, arrest, and abuse
by Trump-ordered Memphis Safe Task Force.
Two completely different headlines
pertaining to the same story.
Ground News puts the coverage side-by-side
so we can spot the bias ourselves.
Their Blindspot feed also shows stories
one side is covering heavily
while the other barely touches them.
Ground News is fully independent
and reader-supported.
I partnered with them to get my viewers
40% off the same plan that I use.
Go to ground.news/peter
Click the link in my description
or scan my QR code
with your phone to get the deal.
Subscribe to Ground News.
Support my reporting.
And take control of how you see the world.
Now back to the story.
[Peter] Midday like today,
bullets aren't flying.
Oh, they are.
It's a lot better now
because of the Memphis Safe Task Force.
We've actually gone a week out here
without a shooting.
Generally, you'll have a shooting
down here every day.
In fact, not long ago,
we had three within a quarter mile
of this intersection in one day.
The Parkway Inn is a ho motel.
-Down there?
-Yeah, and then there's…
You'll see here in a second.
There's Sun Inn and Skyway Inn,
Bellevue Inn right up there.
These are all hourly motels
where women go to turn tricks.
The new pavement is kind of misleading.
But, you know,
there's some science behind that.
If your hood looks nicer,
you're gonna take better care of it.
-Broken glass theory, right?
-Yeah, absolutely.
And so I do buy into that.
And more than anecdotally.
We've seen it play out.
Matter of fact,
where I'm about to take you,
you're gonna see
broken glass theory in action.
All right, so this is Elvis Presley.
That was South Parkway we just turned off.
This is my building right here.
You see my We Fight Monsters sign?
Oh, right here. Nice.
Guys, we're gonna get more into that.
But just want to let you know,
We Fight Monsters.
That's what Ben and Jess are doing.
That's their organization.
Getting people off the streets
into homes like we've seen.
And that's not all you do.
That's just like your passion project.
-You also have a business, right?
-I've got several.
This is the most expensive hobby
in the world.
-Okay, okay.
-But here's the thing, man.
It takes all of this for us to stay clean.
We've tried building businesses
and raising a family.
And we relapsed every time.
We've rebuilt life together
and burned it to the ground twice.
And so this time
we decided to do it different.
And we started the nonprofit
with our excess.
So this is Wilbur Street. All right.
That is the house
where we hit rock bottom.
So I woke up in an empty lot next door
to the trap house in South Memphis,
covered in blood
and had no idea what happened..
This is that empty lot.
It's no longer empty.
And this is that trap house.
This was the first house
that we came back to Memphis
with the intent of shutting down.
It was an active dope house at the time.
This is the window
Lucretia told you about
that my hand went through
and stole all her dope.
They used to do hand-to-hand transactions
through this window.
I have no idea how many people
have been shot in this house.
You can see the gunshots coming back out
because we'd be shooting back.
-Oh right.
We've patched a lot in the house itself
when we renovated it.
Right now the house is boarded up.
We had a couple in here that relapsed
and trashed everything.
And so since they were buying
dope and all that,
we decided we're gonna
board this house up for a little bit
and just let the block calm back down.
You can tell from the construction
this street is still very calm.
And that's crazy for where we're at.
Woodward Street is…
it was insane.
I've gone to jail in this spot
more times than I can count.
My buddy was shot in the head five times
right there, died on the ground.
Another one of my friends
went missing from that house.
She was found up the road.
Her mutilated body left in the cemetery.
Lucretia's brother's been shot
six times in this house.
Four times on one occasion,
two times on another occasion.
Jess and I have been
held at gunpoint in this house.
Removed from this house at gunpoint.
-Recidivism rate is high?
Staggering.
-Like what percent?
-90 plus.
90 plus. Depending on the
demographic you're talking about.
The recidivism rate is staggeringly high.
And the reason for that is
the issues that have people committing
crimes aren't getting addressed.
You're talking generational trauma,
generational cycles of poverty.
I'm not making excuses.
We make the decisions
we make that land us in jail.
But, you know, I wish programs like
the Shelby County Drug Court,
Recovery Court,
Veterans Court, Mental Health Court…
I wish those got
as much funding as our jails get.
Because if you're talking about this
from a taxpayer perspective,
Like, let's say Cody,
who you haven't met yet, stole my car.
That's what he was.
He was a professional car thief. Alright?
He steals my car.
Auto Theft Task Force
builds a case on him.
They arrest Cody. He goes to jail.
My car has been chopped.
I'm never getting that back.
I didn't have insurance.
So it's not like
I'm getting cashed out on that.
Now, as a taxpayer of Shelby County,
I'm footing the bill at 45 grand a year
to keep Cody incarcerated.
I've never been made whole.
So I'm essentially being re-victimized
by him having to be incarcerated.
Whereas today, Cody is five years clean
and is paying taxes,
running a business himself,
managing our men's housing.
And that's because of re-entry.
That's because of, you know, focusing
on the actual causes of the problems
rather than just punitive.
Right?
And some people belong in institutions.
Don't dispute that.
Child molesters,
people that commit sexual violence,
exceptionally violent individuals.
These are the people jails are made for.
There are certain people that have to be
removed from society. You can't fix them.
I firmly believe child molesters
and people that commit sexual violence
are in that category.
The majority of everybody else,
people that commit property crimes,
a random violent crime,
and drug crimes in particular.
Those people, more often than not,
can be fixed
and can be sent right back out
into these communities to change them.
-Okay, let me ask you this question.
My wife and I left San Francisco in '21.
That's when we had a weak DA
that said the criminals are the victims.
You could steal up to $950.
And so there was no stick.
There was plenty of incentive.
-And so we just got more of that.
-Yep, 100%.
So with what you're saying,
recidivism is super high.
You're saying we just gotta
go with a different approach
because if there is no consequence,
then it seems like it multiplies.
-Yes, let me clarify that.
-Yeah.
I am a law and order guy.
I am not saying no consequence.
I would not have gotten clean
if I wasn't getting charged
every other weekend
for possession of narcotics.
Like gonna jail sucks.
It helped me get clean.
So getting booked in jail,
you know, having to do 30 days,
having to do three months,
makes perfect sense.
We need that. We need those consequences.
What I'm saying doesn't make sense is like
when I got arrested
with all the guns and drugs,
I was looking at 20 years in prison.
How is that fixing anything, right?
I needed drug court.
Now I say that and I still
got myself kicked off drug court
because I wasn't ready
to get clean, you know.
But I watch people every single day
come off these same streets,
end up in our drug court house
and do it right.
And so the point I was making is
that we need to focus more
on outcomes-based judicial process
where there's data-backed stuff behind it.
-Right.
-Not decriminalization. God, never.
Like get out of prison
and don't just release like there's…
-You have to go through a reentry process.
-Yeah.
And so to that end,
we've met with the US Attorney's Office,
the Federal Reentry Council,
Bureau of Prisons.
We work with the drug court
every single day.
We work with probation
and parole because these systems in place
is how you prevent
that revolving door from continuing.
This house,
this was mine and Jessica's
personal hell.
And it doesn't look like it today
because we gutted the motherf*cker.
-This was your personal hell?
-This was our personal hell.
The number of hours I spent
in this room wishing I could die.
Yeah, this house is hell.
It's so surreal to be in here.
Yeah.
-So the only way
you stay from going back into this…
-…is doing what you're doing right now.
-Yeah.
'Cause you see it from
a sober perspective firsthand.
You're like, that looks terrible.
I don't want that.
-And then you're helping people.
-Yeah. It's…
I'm a little extra in everything we do.
And so I don't think everybody
needs to go buy the f*cking trap house
where they wish they died to get clean.
But I had to do that. You know, I had to.
I had to try to get the dudes
that used to sell me dope
on a better path
because I knew they were good men.
Lucretia.
I wasn't wrong about her.
She's kept families together
'cause I got her and her sister
and her brother out of this house.
And on paper, that's a narco trafficker.
That's a human trafficker.
That's a violent felon.
On paper, there's no logical reason
she should be doing
what she's doing today.
Yet there's at least a dozen kids
who have parents
in their lives because of her.
And so it takes people
who have actually lived it.
You can't just institutionalize
and put programming in place
that says we're gonna do X.
You have to know these people.
You have to actually have lived it.
You have to have bled
in the trenches with them
to be able to guess who's going to do
what you want them to do.
You're not always gonna get it right.
Two of the guys
that used to sell dope out of this house
that we helped avoid some consequences
and mentored onto a better path.
One of them has since shot somebody
and the other got caught
with five and a half pounds of fentanyl.
You're not always gonna get it right.
But you get 'Creita, Jordan, and Daphne
who are kicking ass today.
And then you've got us. We came out of
the same house. And here we are today.
This house has been used
to put a family back together.
Explain to those that don't do
meth and fent, what's so great?
All it seems like
is terrible from the outside.
What's the draw to that?
Is when you're in it,
it feels just amazing?
No, it was miserable. You just can't stop.
Well, at first it is amazing.
-That's what kinda brings you in.
-Yeah.
Addiction begins with a choice.
You know, that first time,
you made a choice to do it
and it does feel great.
But the problem is,
especially with crack,
you'll spend the rest of your life
chasing that high you had the first time.
And you'll never get it again. Ever.
But you are incapable
of not continuing to chase it.
With opiates, it's different.
Now, fentanyl came into this house
in early 2018.
This block in 2018.
And, you know, Jess and I
both come from a healthcare background.
My first job after the Army in college
was selling drugs for Pfizer.
-She was a medical assistant.
-No way.
We both vehemently
wanted to avoid fentanyl.
We were afraid of it.
We were addicted to heroin.
-'Cause you knew what it was?
-Absolutely.
And, you know,
you're asking what's the draw.
With heroin, first time you shoot up,
it feels like God's giving you a hug.
-It's the most comforting thing on earth.
-Oh, okay.
All your problems go away?
The song Comfortably Numb by Pink Floyd?
That's about heroin.
That's exactly what it is.
[Peter] Okay,
so who's buying these places?
[Ben] People in this community.
That's the goal, I think, for all of us
is to make this community better
for the people that are already here.
Nobody's trying to gentrify South Memphis.
Like, one, it's not gonna work.
-No college students are coming in here?
-100%.
Making this place actually better for the
people that live here and grow up here,
that's something everybody can get behind.
You've seen already, even though we're in
one of the deadliest zip codes in America,
everybody's pretty d*mn cool.
-Yeah, right.
-So that was broken glass theory
kinda in action right there.
One person shows up
making it a little bit better.
-You want the windows up?
-So they don't see the camera.
They're gonna get weirded out
like a motherf*cker if they see that.
They're not used to me bringing
other White folks out here to film.
-All right.
-So this is a very active dope track.
I'm not gonna point out the houses
because I'm not trying
to get anybody rolled up.
We're still working with
the dope boys out here.
I've got two of them
that run houses out here,
have active ongoing cases
in criminal court.
I would like to see them
get on a better path.
One of them, I don't think
there's a chance in hell.
He's had ample opportunity
and he probably needs to be in prison.
You never know.
They surprise you sometimes.
-Okay, so you're a kid growing up here.
What's your life looking like
for the most part?
You're selling weed by the time you're 12.
Like best case.
And it's to help mama
put bread on the table.
- Yeah, but can't she get welfare?
Oh, they're getting all that.
But here's the thing.
When mom's addicted to fent or crack,
she's selling her food stamps
the day she gets them
for 50 cents on the dollar.
There's a lot of stores
around here you can go
and they'll buy your stamps.
It's illegal but they do it.
It's also a lot more expensive to be poor
than it is to be just above poor.
When you're having to rent a room
and you're in a food desert
there's not healthy food options.
It's Zoo Zoos and Wham Whams.
Nobody's got cars.
It's just a very difficult cycle
to get out of.
And I can say that
because I've been stuck in it myself.
The food desert argument here would be
why do you want to set up a shop
when you're gonna have
so much robbery going on?
-Bro.
-Right?
That right there, where it's
DG Market now, it was a Walgreen’s.
Then it was something else.
How do you put a Walgreen’s
out of business, man?
And it's shoplifting.
-Is it the Indian markets that come in?
Is that about it?
Those don't even last.
See you'll have an Indian corner store
or a lot of them
are Iranian run now I think.
-Those guys have got courage, huh?
-They do.
And by and large,
they're cool as sh*t too.
-I love those guys. They have fun.
-Right.
I have an international audience.
People are gonna see this
from other parts of the world.
-And be like, yeah, that's not that bad.
-[Ben laughs]
-Right?
-Right.
It's a little shabby, but you got
sidewalks and the pavement isn't dirt.
And, you know, these houses
just need paint and a little love.
-Yep. Well, on paper, last year,
this was 400% deadlier
for a civilian than Ukraine.
500% deadlier than Iraq or Afghanistan.
It doesn't look like it, but it is.
Jess and I used to live in a $700 truck
in this lot right here
with our two-year-old.
-Oh, my God.
When was this nice? 50s?
-Yeah, probably the 50s.
Most of these homes were built in the 30s.
And so I would say
it was definitely nice back then,
but it's just steadily declined ever since.
-And to be fair, we're showing
just the hood right now today.
There are beautiful hoods here.
-Right? And beautiful architecture.
-Yeah.
And, like,
I have that in another video
'cause you could think
it's all like this, and it's not.
This is Stax Recording Studio,
the birthplace of soul music.
This is why this area
is called Soulsville.
You can even see
the little Soulsville sign right there.
-This is a tourist stop?
-Oh, yeah. Big time.
Okay, so a little piece
of brightness in the hood.
Well, that was
the backdrop to three murders
in less than seven days
about a month ago.
It looks like it should be nice.
And I'll sit out here
and b*tch about the problems all day long,
but I don't claim to have the answer.
There's a lot of answers.
Getting men to be fathers out here
would go so far.
You have dudes getting raised.
Often by aunts or grandmothers,
not even their mother.
Men need to have men in their lives.
You need a strong male
in your life to teach you things.
-Or the gang's gonna do it.
And if you pay attention to social media,
the things that are important
to a lot of these guys out here,
like, you know, designer clothes.
Like sh*t men shouldn't care about, right?
That is a very strange thing for a man
to be posting on Facebook about.
But you'll see more often than not,
that is the content that is
getting echoed out here.
We need men focused on
building enterprise,
building businesses,
creating economic opportunity and jobs.
And if you pay attention to rap lyrics.
Obviously, we're in
a very heavily Black community.
I was the only cracker out here for years.
It's becoming cool again for the Black
entrepreneur and the Black father.
-It is. The lyrics are coming around.
I think the timing for what we're trying
to convey out here is God ordained.
I think we got really lucky.
You'll see if we get to encounter
any of the dope boys today.
Like, they want it
to be better out here, too.
Their kids got to grow up out here.
Their baby mamas,
their moms are out here on these streets.
Nobody wants it to
remain what it is now.
Nobody really just knows how
to go about making change.
And I think one of the things that
we've gotten good at
is showing people that
this is so easy a crackhead can do it.
Just put some effort in and try
to make one thing better at a time.
And what will end up happening is
what you saw in Wilbur to Melrose.
Other people are gonna
come along behind you.
They just need somebody
to lead the charge.
I think it was Mark Twain that said
in the early days of a revolution,
a patriot is a hard to find,
something to that effect.
But when the risk of
being the leader in that goes away,
the more timid guys
will come out of the woodwork.
You have to have the more timid guy.
You have to have everybody coming
together trying to drive change out here.
It's not something one man can do.
-Okay, so you grow up in a house,
your parents are split up,
your mom's on dope, your dad's not there.
I mean, you don't have
many positive examples.
-That's the problem, right?
-That's a big part of the problem, yeah.
And also, mentality,
easy for me to say
because I don't live here,
but I was in Savannah recently
talking to this guy.
It was off camera and he's like,
how do you do it, man?
And I'm like, what?
He's like, you travel like this
and you don't cheat on your wife.
I'm like, I don't know.
I love her and she's great.
That's not an option?
He looked at me like I hiked Everest
without a shirt and no oxygen.
It was the most amazing feat ever.
And I'm like, man,
you just blew up your family again
and you keep cheating on women.
That's just not, I mean…
Mindset's a huge problem.
And I'll get the same reaction
from guys out here
when you sit down and have a
heart-to-heart with a gang member
or a dope boy and you drop on them
that you don't have to go to prison.
Nobody has to go to prison.
-They think they're going no matter what?
-Yeah.
It's like, this is a part of life
and that gets accepted.
Infidelity, violent crime,
all of these things
that should seem so foreign to most of us,
it is an accepted part of life out here.
It's so normal that for them
to grasp anything other than that
is like a shocking, massive revelation.
But it's a very important revelation
to get out there.
If you can start getting it to be
generationally accepted,
you should not be incarcerated.
That is not… it doesn't have to happen.
You know, that's kind of a big deal.
And the sanctity of marriage,
the importance of a home,
family dinners, things that most of us
probably take for granted, they're,
you know, that's like something
that happens on TV.
That's kinda sad.
Do you see on a governmental level,
what's the strategy?
You would know better than me since
you're in the thick of it here
What do you think the strategy is?
Let it be, let it destroy itself or…
I think both political parties
leverage the hood
as a con for self interest
I'm seeing Black America at large
get played by both parties.
This is not a Democrat or Republican issue.
They're playing the Black community.
They're playing on poverty, violent crime
to further their own self interest
and honestly to get reelected.
My faith in the institution of
American government has fallen so much
in the last several years
because of the work we do
I don't see government
as actually really wanting to solve thing.
I don't see the politicians
that are out here clammering
for everybody's vote and claiming
to have done so much
for the hood actually do sh*t.
I don't. For the most part,
especially at the federal level,
our government uses the hood
as a means to an end.
They use Black America
-'Cause if you get that vote you win.
-Absolutely.
-Or it's gonna help.
Or you get money
legislated away for self interest.
You look at the fraud that's going on
all around our country, federal programs,
and so many of them hinge on your ability
to sell that idea to the Black community.
I have been waiting for
the successful Black community to show up
and shoulder this load with us and it's
not happened and that's frustrating.
You've got a lot of very successful
Black businessmen in this city
and all around the country
who came out of Memphis
and we're out here trying to make
the worst hood in America
a safer place for kids.
And we've got metrics to back it up,
it's not just me saying
we're making it better.
We're objectively making this place better.
The crime has dropped significantly.
You've got construction happening
on streets in South Memphis
that hasn't happened in a hundred years.
Right? And there's no way to say it's not
because of what we've done out here.
I feel especially
our elected officials from that community
should be showing up out here.
There's some great art in here.
-This is beautiful.
-That's why I wanted to bring you here.
This is really cool.
There is so much
hidden potential in the hood.
-Right look at that.
-People just don't realize it.
-No, it's so true.
Every time you come out here
the art's different.
This is still active,
there's still kids skating out here.
-Look at that.
[Ben] We're getting into Midtown now.
You'll have million dollar homes
in a second.
Matter of fact,
I believe Scientology owns this one.
-No way.
-Yeah.
-That is a trip.
I mean that's literally 30 seconds.
-30 seconds, man.
-Does the crime come over here?
-100% yeah.
-100%?
Usually the crime's
gonna happen on the streets.
Home invasions are exceedingly rare
when you're talking about normal citizens.
If you're selling dope, your house
is getting broken into I promise.
People pretty much just accept it
but that being said,
you just walked through the ultra hood
and saw nobody's bothering you.
As long as you act like
you're where you're supposed to be
you're not gonna become a victim.
Most are crimes of opportunity.
If they can target somebody that looks like
a victim they're 100% gonna do that.
-[Jess] This is Central Barbecue.
-This is her favorite restaurant.
I love barbecue period
but Central is so good.
-And Memphis obviously legendary.
-Legendary barbecue, yeah.
It's better here than anywhere else
and I will fight people over that.
-Thank you so much.
-Yes, sir.
-Do you love it? Is it amazing.
-Oh, it's amazing.
Okay.
Okay, cool.
-[Peter] Thank you.
-No problem.
All right, pulled pork sandwich.
-What is that, Ben?
-Barbecue nachos.
Barbecue nachos.
-That's a little bit of everything, huh?
-Little bit of everything.
In the next couple years we need to have
about $10 million raised
to open our own treatment center.
-We already have the building.
-Okay.
Once we have that done
it'll be off to the races
That'll be generating revenue.
-How's it generating revenue.
-Treatment center. Insurance.
-Okay.
-Yeah.
And state reimbursement.
So why do you think that link of the chain
is broken with treatment centers?
Just bad stigma?
Or what is it? 'Cause it seems like…
-I don't know that it's broken.
-We need more of that, right?
People that are in that space in Memphis
and probably nationwide are very
guarded.
They view every other
center as competition.
There's not a lot of collaboration.
And it's easy for us not to look at anybody
as competition 'cause this mission
is not my livelihood.
My income doesn't depend on this.
In fact it actually hurts my income.
Right and the more I get into the stories
around the country, the more I'm wary
when an income is
fully off something like this.
It's sketchy.
Especially if they're driving
a truck like yours.
-Ah, what's this dude doing with the money?
-Bingo.
And I hate to say it,
it's more often than not
where I see situations where it's like
I love the cause, the mission, and then
greed comes when money comes in.
-Well…
-You make no money from…
This costs me
six figures personally every year.
-You have a well performing business?
-Yeah.
…supports you.
Despite talking about that often and loudly
people still see me
and my collection of muscle cars
and my truck and somehow
get it in their head that
that the non-profit
has paid for any of that.
I'm like, no, I had all of these things
before I had a non-profit.
Right.
The thing that frustrates me the most is
non-profit financials are public.
You don't even have to
do the research yourself.
You can ask Chat GPT how much
does Ben make from We Fight Monsters?
It'll tell you straight up, zero dollars.
-'Cause it can see our financials.
-Okay.
Great sandwich by the way.
Really good barbecue.
Mmm.
I just love barbecue.
Tender.
Okay, so what's the five year plan
if you have one?
We'll have 777,
our treatment center opened up.
We'll have a trade school,
job skills training.
A full reentry program, youth services.
And I won't have to be
the face of it anymore.
-You don't want to be?
-Hm-mm.
I want to focus on my businesses
and my family.
You don't want to work on
anything else in this space?
I want to tell myself I don't
but I know that's a lie.
I'm incapable of not doing this.
I want to expand our work of reentry.
I want to have more done
with youth programming.
-Okay.
-That's a difficult space…
…to be effective and that's a big gap.
Just you're dealing with state, parents?
Liability.
Legality.
Public perception.
Recovery period is
a tough space to operate in.
Because there are so many grifters.
Right.
There are so many schemes and scams
and it's impossible
to not get lumped in with those people.
Doesn't matter how successful
I am on the for profit side.
-Yeah.
-People are always gonna see
Ben just made a post asking for money
for this but Ben has a…
A $90,000 truck and a 1970 GTX.
Okay, well Ben's already given
a lot of money to this.
What are you doing for your business?
What's your main business?
It's actually shifting, ones taking off.
For years my primary business
has been a company called Black Rifle.
We do data intelligence and digital media
for the firearms industry.
Gun companies can't go advertise in Google.
-They can't advertise on Facebook.
-Okay.
We created a platform that allows
them to advertise across ad exchanges
like they were with Google and Facebook
and it's been very successful.
Then we started
another company called Once American
that does open source intelligence
targeting in investigative work.
Basically we leverage agentic AI to
scour petabytes of information.
to do intelligence work on bad actors.
And it can do in two minutes
what it would take a human a day or two.
Give me an example how that works.
There's a bad actor…
Let's say Homeland Security has
a trafficking case
tied back to an email address.
I can take that email, run it through
and give you that guy's full identity
I'm talking down to
the VIN number of his vehicle.
And they're able to go
action that as law enforcement.
Gotcha.
And so that's actually starting to
take off really well right now.
I bet. I bet.
[Peter] We're going to North Memphis
which is a totally different hood, right?
-Totally different hood,
very little crossover.
You hear me talk about street gangs,
They're very lowly organized in Memphis.
The fact they get hit with RICO charges,
racketeering and organized crime
is hilarious to me.
Street gangs in Memphis are not like that.
It's not like there's blood in, blood out,
they're just cliques, man.
And for the most part
a lot of the violence is intra-clique.
It's they're fighting each other.
-Okay. So North Memphis, rough,
just like South Memphis or different?
It depends on who you ask.
Statistically, it's nowhere near as bad
as South Memphis.
But, you know,
you hit some of these neighborhoods,
it's gonna feel a lot worse,
if that makes sense.
It looks worse.
This is like the weirdest little
compound area
and it is full of addicts.
They closed it down because of black mold.
Now it's opened again.
But you know what?
There are a lot of just
good working class people in here.
But addiction is
a big problem out here, man.
These people had started squatting
in these when they were shut down
and they built barricades out of pallets.
It was like some
real meth lab looking sh*t.
In fact, they were probably cooking meth.
Some of them don't even have power.
It looks a lot better now because
they slapped paint and new roof on.
But dude, these things,
like they're rough on the inside.
So guy just recycling stuff.
Is that that story?
Never know, man.
That could be his family.
Now sometimes they'll be scrapping sh*t.
There are a lot of scrap yards.
I didn't see what he had.
They'll pick up scrap metal.
But the scrap yards out here are allies
when you're trying to get intel
on trafficking survivors
who might be scrapping sh*t.
We had one guy gonna look out
for a pedophile for us.
-Okay, so what's the trafficking scene
these days with women?
So trafficking in Memphis
is largely dope-fueled prostitution.
We've sat down with human traffickers,
convicted traffickers, and asked them,
if you were gonna start that back up,
how would you go through that process?
And none of them said they're gonna kidnap
girls and get them addicted to dope.
Because they don't have to.
There are plenty of people
who are already addicted.
There are plenty of girls
who already have problems at home.
They're gonna be easily exploitable
because they have trust issues,
unmet needs.
They have basic needs unmet.
Food, clothing, housing.
You go meet any of those needs.
And before long
you're gonna have essentially a slave.
-Especially if they're already addicted.
-Okay.
And so trafficking
more often than not begins
with a girl who has already
maybe used her body to fund her addiction.
And just falls in with the wrong dude
who acts like he's gonna take care of her.
And what ends up happening is
he's now got him a new victim to traffic.
As long as you keep her fed with dope,
she's gonna keep doing what's asked.
So just pimp-ho relationship basically?
-100%. Yep.
-Okay. How many workers
do these pimps have typically?
Most of them will have,
you know, two to three main ones.
And then they'll have those
referred to as the bottoms.
Some of them have just one primary bottom
and they'll go recruit more.
I think the most we've ever tied back
to one trafficker is what, seven?
-Yeah.
They're not big rings here.
Jess will end up working these cases
because a lot of them
start on sex-ad sites.
And I'm just not gonna sit there and…
But they'll tweak out on these things
and start identifying girls based on ads.
I'm seeing signs of trafficking.
I've tied this number back
to this guy using the platform
that Homeland Security uses.
You'll tie that back to the trafficker.
We've identified rings that'll operate
at Airbnbs in Houston, New Orleans,
Memphis, Miami, Tampa.
And they'll own these Airbnbs.
Like, these are big deal trafficking rings
that are run by dudes and their bottoms.
And so those end up getting
kind of large sometimes.
And those are the kind of cases
we'll work with,
you know, three-letter agencies.
-Where is it the worst in the country?
It's pretty much uniform
across urban, metro area America.
You're seeing this everywhere.
You see it everywhere. I think, and we've
worked counter-trafficking operations
and recovered women all over the country.
I think where it's gonna be the worst
is where you have
a larger immigrant population
and you've got people that
you can really exploit
in a number of different ways.
Not just based around addiction.
But like if you're running an operation
that involves a passport scam.
Like a Chinese illicit massage parlor
or something like that.
Those are where
it gets really, really ugly.
And so cities, like Memphis does not have
a very large immigrant population
compared to Atlanta, Houston, DFW.
Okay.
Memphis and St. Louis are a lot alike
in our demographics and our issues.
Atlanta and Houston are a lot alike
in their issues.
And so the more nefarious side
of human trafficking
turns up in those cities.
Here, most of it is based around addiction.
So this is an area
known as Speedway Terrace.
Not a great part of town,
but it's one of my favorite places.
Now all of these homes
are about a century old.
-What are these going for?
-It depends on how they've been renovated.
One right down there
got renovated really nice, like Airbnb.
And they were selling it for,
what, $270,000?
-So in Memphis you might get an Airbnb
and not know what hood you're in?
Right.
-And you could end up in the hood.
-Absolutely. [laughs]
We call this our old men's home
or the retirement home.
And it's not intentional.
It's just usually where
all of our old vets end up.
Because our other men's house
is reserved for drug court clients.
Which not always,
but usually ends up being younger guys.
Two of my favorite guys on earth, man.
How y'all doing?
-How's it going, bro? Love you, dude.
-Good to see you.
-Hey, buddy. How's it going?
-I'm all right.
-How you doing? Peter.
-How you doing?
-Nice to meet you,
-Gary, Peter, Peter, Gary.
This is Drenon.
-Drenon. Nice to meet you, sir.
-How you doing?
Doing well.
He met your sister earlier
and your granddaughter.
Okay. Rekaya. The little girl.
-That's his granddaughter.
-Nice.
She's doing good, man.
-How are things going right now for you?
-Hey, fine, man.
Going pretty good for me, man.
-Sober life.
-How long you been sober?
Well, '23.
Since '23? Oh, nice.
-And you, sir?
-13 months.
-This time.
-Okay, this time, how many relapses?
At least six.
-Oh, wow.
So how you holding on this time?
This time I get more active.
Ben gave me the opportunity
to be the manager of the house.
That helps a lot.
And then I'll tell you what,
what really made me
take help this time was
When I come back in here,
I come back in with my head down.
I done messed up again and again.
And that ain't something
that I choose to do.
That's something that just happens
for whatever reason.
But when I come in here and Ben and Cody
and them, they never look down on me.
He just say, hey, you got it this time.
I'm glad to see you back.
And that means more than anything.
And it pushes me forward.
I want to do that for somebody else.
You know?
-And he's done it for a lot
of somebody else's at this point.
A lot!
When they give me
the opportunity to do it,
you don't know how much it means
for somebody that…
I know I've relapsed six times.
I know I've accumulated
more charges in the last five years
than I had in my whole life.
But for him not to look down on me,
for him to say, you got it this time.
For whatever reason, it just took hold.
And then me being given
the opportunity to be proactive,
to volunteer and do other things.
And I don't want to let him down again.
I don't want to let me down again.
-You never let me down, man.
And he showed me that.
-Can we walk in here? Is that cool?
How many of you guys in here right now?
-I think it's six.
-Six?
For six guys, you keep a…
How you doing, sir?
For six guys, you keep a pretty tight ship.
Three, four…
It holds 12.
It's low right now.
-I've never seen a place
with six guys this clean.
Oh, brother,
they keep this place spotless.
-Good work.
-How you doing?
I'm Ben.
-Nice to meet you.
-Nice to meet you too.
This is my wife, Jess.
-Peter.
-Nice to meet y'all.
-Your name is?
-I'm Gary.
-Gary?
-Yes, sir.
[Jess] You got here
not too long ago, right?
-Two weeks ago.
-Okay.
-[Peter] How's it going, Gary?
-It's going good.
-You guys all get along?
-Yes we do.
Who's not doing the dishes, huh?
Everybody does the dishes.
Week at a time.
Oh, this is great.
Yeah, so they have their own lockers
and keep their own stuff.
This is like a community kitchen, so…
It's all organized. Look at that.
They got the parts of the fridge.
Yeah, we had another guy that was
running it a while back, and he was a…
I'll just say it.
He's a horrible human being.
So we had to get him out,
and then Gary's in it now,
and it's always been big
to keep it very tidy and clean.
-Yeah, it looks great.
It's more orderly,
and it gives them more structure.
God, they're doing really good.
It looks beautiful.
Yeah, for six guys? No dishes in the sink?
-Come on.
-Yeah.
That's a first.
And it makes me feel even better
seeing the men that come through here.
Some of them we used to smoke crack
with Jordan back in the trap house.
-And to have him here now, clean.
-No way.
It's just an amazing feeling.
You know what I love the most about this?
It's a feeling and I'm sure
it will come through on camera.
These people love you guys.
There's a deep bond.
-Yeah.
-We've been through a lot with these guys.
Both the ones we knew in
active addiction and the ones since.
You get to stand by them
through thick and thin.
When we were in the house at Wilbur,
I told you a good friend
overdosed and died in there.
That was his wife.
Yeah, so like, we go back.
We go way back.
-And you got drug testing here.
-Oh, yeah.
You gotta have accountability, man.
It's tough when somebody fails.
The way these houses
were historically run,
this has been a halfway house
20 years in Memphis.
I was court-ordered into the one
up the street. We own that one now, too.
I got kicked out in eight days
'cause I failed a drug screen.
But that historically,
that's how it was run.
If you failed, you're out. You know?
And it's still that way today,
but it's not just you're out.
It's, alright, you failed this screen.
You're out of here today.
But I can take you to detox,
and I can save your bed.
Or you can just hit the streets.
And so, we've had a lot of guys opt
to just start over, you know?
And that's what it takes sometimes.
For some of us, like me, we're dumb.
And you gotta hit the streets
and go suffer some more, you know?
Guys, thanks for letting us
crash this morning.
-Keep up the great work.
-I love you, man.
Hey man, thank you.
Thank you, man. Thank you.
Thank you. I f*ckin' love you, bro.
-Gary, thanks, man.
-Take care.
We'll see you, man.
-Nice to meet you.
-Take care, brother.
-So, I haven't seen that much of this.
-You won't.
The police typically
won't tolerate that sh*t.
There are some places
where it'll pop up and…
-He probably coming to yell at you.
-Yeah.
-It is horrendous.
-What? The public schools?
The public school system here is just…
And there's so much drama
around the school system right now.
They gave up their charter.
They can't run a school system.
That's the problem.
Nobody is proficient at grade level.
I forget the percentage that is actually
even able to read when they graduate.
But it is abhorrent.
And to look at that
and then expect any different
from the next generation of Memphis…
It feels a little disingenuous.
Like, you can't throw kids into
such a hot garbage mess of public school
and expect change to happen.
If anything, it's gonna get worse.
You can't blame it all on the schools.
It's the home life, right?
Absolutely. There's a myriad of factors.
The talent and the heart is leaving
the teaching profession by and large.
But also, you've got kids
coming into schools
acting like grown adults that have…
They don't attach consequences
to actions at all.
They don't process
that the teachers have authority.
Or if they do
it means absolutely nothing to them.
That's all society's
and the adults' fault, right?
-For letting it go to that?
-Absolutely.
Because if I was a kid,
and I did as a kid,
I pushed it right to the edge.
100%. I did, too.
And if the edge was further away,
I would have pushed it further.
Yep. Absolutely.
That's what adolescents do.
And that's part of
what makes America great
is that our kids push limits, right?
-But you've got to have guardrails up.
-Yeah.
And there have to be,
you know, firm and swift consequences
when we push too hard
against those guardrails.
You don't have that in Memphis.
You've got kids acting like grown folks.
I think the largest driver of violent crime
in this city currently is probably kids.
You know, 12 to 16 years old.
That's a scary prospect for a teacher.
Society needs to get back to a meritocracy
where we move forward
based on the merits of our actions.
I don't feel entitled
to special treatment because I'm White
or because I'm an addict in recovery.
And I think that's how a lot of how
we operate as a society got off-kilter
is because
we started paying more attention to
what makes somebody different
rather than exceptional.
We need to get back to
rewarding exceptionalism.
And push each other to become the best
version of ourselves that we can be.
That's the only way
any of this gets any better.
I do enough out here
that when I lay my head on my pillow,
I know I couldn't have done more.
Objectively looking at
all the problems Memphis has,
it is too much
for one organization to stop.
It doesn't mean
we haven't had major impact.
that we haven't done great things.
But I know the problems here
are far too big for just us to tackle.
They're far too big
for just law enforcement to tackle.
Which is why we leaned on the White House,
leaned on the Memphis Safe Task Force.
So now we do have the playing field
leveled more than we did.
So now I think if the right people
can lean on the Department of Education,
on HUD, Health and Human services
to get all the other angles attacked.
Memphis could have
a renaissance inside three years.
We've already gone from the deadliest city
in America to off the top ten list
in a matter of months.
But the second these feds leave Memphis
all that sh*t's coming right back
-I haven't seen any feds though yet at all.
-Have you seen Highway Patrol?
-What's that?
-Have you seen Tennessee Highway Patrol?
-Yeah.
-They're riding with them.
-Okay.
-Yeah.
Wait til something pops off,
you'll see all of 'em.
-40 of them.
-You'll see 40 roll up, dude.
The response time is insane.
In a good way right now.
The overwhelming response,
shock and awe factor is a big deal too.
Hell, they'll even have National Guard
show up for d*mn shoplifting.
It's crazy. It's a Band-Aid.
-But if you're saying
these kids are graduating school
a lot of them not even being able to read.
Then I mean common sense says…
It's not gonna get better.
It's not gonna get better, you know?
You have to tackle that metric right there.
I have to make young men in this hood
more likely to be in college or have a job
than they are to be dead or incarcerated.
Right now it's the flip of that,
we have to turn that around.
I think to turn that around it's gonna take
tackling the school system,
tackling just a whole host of human
problems that are far too great for me.
Like I'm good at
helping people out of addiction.
That's kinda my thing.
I'm not good at helping people
graduate school reading on grade level.
We need a lot more dumped into this city.
People don't have any idea
how bad this place is.
None whatsoever.
If I bring people from Memphis
to where we live in Georgia
they're blown away and they think
Forsythe County, Georgia is a unicorn.
Whereas in reality Memphis is the unicorn.
This place is unlike
anywhere else I've ever lived
and I've lived in 28 cities and 14 states.
This place is very different
from the rest of America.
That's the dichotomy that is Memphis.
It feels fine, it feels safe,
all the people are cool.
-But we're…
-Until you piss them off.
Until they burn your house down.
Until they come burn your house down, yeah.
-They're quick to react.
-Yeah.
-…I would too
-Yeah, that's a tear down.
[Peter] When did this thing get burnt?
[man] About a month or two.
Month or two?
-It was cold when that place burned down.
Three months.
So had to scare you guys
seeing this go up in flames.
-Yeah, y'all lucky.
Got up to go to the bathroom,
it was cold as hell.
You could feel the heat like summertime.
-Ooh boy.
It burnt for a while.
-Gotta go all the way down.
-Was it your old neighbor
who set it on fire?
-It had been vacant a while.
-It had been vacant?
Yeah.
How's everything in the hood otherwise?
Otherwise normal, you know, sh*t happens.
-But a lot of stuff's
getting built up around here.
-It ain't bad as people put on to be.
It's just a normal hood
-You a waiter
or you go around with the apron?
-I work at the Rendezvous, I'm a waiter.
-Nice.
[Ben] Oh, hell yeah.
Next time we need to take you
to Rendezvous, that's great barbecue.
They kinda blow it up with the crime thing.
Blow it out of proportion.
You feel okay walking around at night?
Without a doubt.
I actually used to run 15, 20 laps.
-Down the center.
-Oh, yeah?
Yeah, I used to run 20 laps
down the center back and forth.
-You got Junior doing that?
I stay in German Town,
this my old home.
I got another home now
I work out in my garage.
-German Town?
-Yeah.
-Are you German?
-Not at all.
[laughter]
How's it out there?
I feel like it's the same as here.
No issues.
-It's just East Memphis now.
Right, it's just East Memphis.
-How many kids you got?
-This is my mom and son.
Okay.
Two sons and a daughter.
-Mom, you're looking fresh.
-Mom's staying here.
D*mn.
-All right, man.
-All the best.
Come on down to see us at Rendezvous.
-Appreciate you.
-Thank you, appreciate you.
-That's generally the kind of interaction
you will have with Memphis people.
They're good people in the end.
Just really good people.
Some have gone down a bad path
and made a few bad choices.
There are some actual bad people here
but for the most part
these are good d*mn people.
-People come up to you,
the smile, they want to talk.
There's no attitude, you're not from here.
-No.
-No, never.
You'll never get treated that way.
You're very welcomed here.
-That's true.
-Everywhere I've gone.
That' comes from
being an underdog I think.
-I think so too.
-Having a bad reputation.
There's humility there.
A sense of humility in the city
that I've never seen anywhere else.
Everybody's not standing around thinking
they're better than anybody else.
Everybody's cool with everybody
and that's why I love Memphis.
-Everybody's in a struggle together here.
There is an us versus them
mentality sometimes
but never at a street level.
On social media, in the news it's always…
And a lot of it goes back to race,
I'm not gonna dance around that,
in media. and on social media.
At a street level it doesn't exist.
-You think the media pumps that up?
-Hell yeah, they do.
I'll tell you why.
Media makes their money from ad revenue.
Ad revenue is driven by web traffic.
And I run a few publisher sites,
I know how they operate.
anything that generates controversy,
gets people arguing, sharing, pissed off,
texting it to mama, screenshot it,
that's how you make money in media.
The news outlets, we've created
a self fulfilling prophecy actually
because we're incapable of
not engaging with things
that we see online that piss us off.
What we're doing when we engage
is we're feeding the beast
and telling that outlet
run more content like this.
-Right.
They look at the analytics, like,
oh, that did great.
Yeah, and invariably
it's the things that get people fighting
that generate the most revenue.
Which sucks because it makes everybody
think we're supposed to hate each other
but in reality, my buddy Scott, man,
I love the way he pronounces this,
the digitally re-presented world.
Not represented, re-presented.
-Oh, yeah.
-You get it?
I love the way he does that and it's
so true because we're being given a
re-presentation of reality.
Yep.
Political ideology will collapse
on first contact with human suffering.
And the more you get out on the streets
and engage with other human beings
who are suffering in the same fight
you are, you're gonna see that.
That is your typical Memphis interaction.
People are just good people
They're not asking
"Why you filming me and my mom?"
-Yeah, right.
-They're just talking.
If anyone looks suspect it's me.
[Ben laughs]
-Right?
-Or me.
-Oh, here we go, this is Graceland.
-Yeah.
So this is his airplane,
they got a concert venue over here.
This is his house.
-That's Elvis' house? No way!
-That's Elvis' house.
Look at the quality of the road here.
-Okay, so Elvis was living in the hood
but it wasn't the hood at the time.
Correct, this was working class back then.
-How you doing, man?
See y'alls vlog so I wanted to get in it.
Yeah, what's going on in the hood?
All good?
I ain't from the hood,
I'm from the suburbs.
Do you love it?
-It's okay.
-It's cool?
-Race ya.
-[giggling]
[Ben] Turbo Diesel.
-Nice, holy sh*t! This thing's got juice.
It does.
So we're at your warehouse.
Yeah, this is our warehouse
and I don't want to steal Jess' thunder
So I'm going to let her give you
the background on what it is today.
I opened this place
as a job skills training thing.
We were gonna teach vets and dudes
coming off the streets woodworking.
So we started this brand
making cutting boards.
We had our Afghan daughter
working here, dope boys…
-Afghan daughter?!
-Yeah. We adopted a girl from Afghanistan.
-During the collapse we got her here.
-Nice.
-Were you in the military?
-Very briefly.
But we worked the Afghan evacuation
from '21, we ran 68 safe houses there.
-No way.
-Yeah, it was wild.
-A whole 'nother video.
-Whole 'nother video, yeah.
-Hood Mart?
-Hood Mart, baby.
[Jess] What you're seeing right here
started in my towel closet
when I was in active addiction.
Ben told you before
that we had multiple businesses
while we were getting high.
We had an addiction
but also a lot of money.
And I've always wanted
to help people my entire life.
So when I was in active addiction
in my closet I would take a bunch of money
get deodorant,
shampoo, soaps, anything I could,
and I'd have
a whole little Walmart in my closet.
So when we went down to South Memphis
to see our drug buddies and prostitutes
I would bring my stuff and give it away.
Then we went homeless, lost everything.
So it's always been my dream
to have a place that's like Goodwill
but nobody has to pay for anything.
As stupid as that sounds.
And that's what this place is.
You're seeing all this wood right here
because when we first opened it
Ben's business partner, Robert,
he is a woodworking guy.
He loves working with wood.
He's very good at it.
So we would have men
that were unemployable.
They had felonies,
couldn’t get hired, just out of prison,
we would bring them here
and let them make cutting boards.
And so they would get a skill
They would have a paycheck.
That since has kinda…
you can only keep that going for so long.
When the woodworking shop
kinda went away, we just…
-Oh, wow.
-This used to be all I had.
All that was donated.
When you have nothing and you've
been homeless and you finally get better
and finally get an apartment.
you have nothing to put in it
and nothing for your kids.
You almost want to go get high again.
Like there's no hope.
So this is a place of hope.
This is a place where kids
can pick out the toys they want
and mothers and fathers
can get shoes and clothes
to go to the interview to get the job
to keep the money coming in.
And these are things
a lot of people don't think about.
Normal people, they're like, go get
some interview clothes, go get a job.
Sometimes you don't have interview clothes
and don't have two pennies to go get 'em.
So this is…
And like this even,
some women have never had this.
Some women have
never been able to feel beautiful
and to have clothes
that they consider fancy.
So that's another thing too.
I don't know if we have them anymore.
But we used to have
prom dresses up here for girls that
mama didn't have money
to buy them a dress.
That's a huge thing.
So we try to have every single thing
that anybody could ever want
and we just give it for free
because we're not paying for it
and I'm not gonna make you pay for it.
[Peter] All right guys, that was awesome.
Love what you're doing.
Anything else you want to say?
-We covered a lot of ground today.
-Lot of ground.
Didn't even get to see the half of it.
We were pretty candid with you
about some challenges we were facing.
But the take away, Peter,
is that if we can't
get the wrap around part of this right.
All the ground we've gained
is just gonna be lost again.
We have to bring
the education system back around.
We have to bring things like reentry,
job skills training, economic opportunity,
parenting classes.
We gotta shift the mentality in Memphis
and if we can't get all of that done,
then what have we really accomplished?
Let me say that in a different way,
we've made a big impact in a lot of lives.
I don't want to take away from that
and if you ask them
we've changed their entire world
and that's a great thing.
But I didn't set out to change
one person's world.
I set out to change an entire city
and to do that
I guess this is my way of acknowledging
we still got a long way to go
and I got a lot to figure out.
-It's awesome you guys.
It comes from a good place.
Place of passion and purpose
and guys, I want to let you know
We Fight Monsters, link is down below.
They got a great website.
-If you want to be part of this…
-Check our YouTube out too.
Check YouTube out,
they got all sorts of great content.
If you feel like giving,
that link is down below.
Guys, thanks for that awesome day.
It's a great window
and this is how we learn.
-Exactly right, brother.
-Yeah.
And thank you guys
for coming on that journey.
Until the next one.
[jazz music]